<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Alice Feurtey</title>
    <link>https://afeurtey.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://afeurtey.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2022 11:45:16 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://afeurtey.github.io/media/icon_hud0dbf17b8928d9e0d9e2422aaf422cc6_1197_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://afeurtey.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Global spread and adaptation of a major crop pathogen</title>
      <link>https://afeurtey.github.io/project/thousands_zt_genomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2022 11:45:16 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://afeurtey.github.io/project/thousands_zt_genomes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an ongoing project and is described here only for information. The figures are from talks I have made and they are likely to change as this project evolves and until it gets published officially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human activity has a tremendous impact on the evolutionary trajectories of many species worldwide. Global trade of agricultural goods contributes to the dispersal of domesticated species but also of their pathogens, reshaping species distributions to include new environments and climates. In the agricultural context, humans partially control the evolution of crop species as well as some environmental variables, thus imposing selective pressure on crop pathogens. Understanding how pathogens surmount control strategies and cope with new climates is crucial to predicting the future impact of crop pathogens in a changing world.
&lt;em&gt;Zymoseptoria tritici&lt;/em&gt; is a major bread and durum wheat pathogen, and causes significant damage in wheat cultivation. It was previously discovered that the center-of-origin of &lt;em&gt;Z. tritici&lt;/em&gt; is the Middle-East, where its sister species are infecting wild grasses. It was also found that the speciation of &lt;em&gt;Z. tritici&lt;/em&gt; happened at the same time as the domestication of its host. &lt;em&gt;Z. tritici&lt;/em&gt; is now reported in most wheat-growing regions of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using more than a thousand isolates of &lt;em&gt;Z. tritici&lt;/em&gt;, we assembled the largest-to-date number of genomes from a fungal plant pathogen species in order to retrace worldwide invasion routes of this species and ongoing genetic exchange among major wheat-growing regions. We identified eleven genetic clusters (see image below), and an early split between the populations of the Middle-East/Africa and the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://afeurtey.github.io/images/1000_Zt_Pop_str.png&#34; alt=&#34;Map of the world displaying the 11 genetic clusters and population tree&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reconstructing the evolutionary history of the species, we uncovered its impact on adaptive genetic variation and on the evolution of the pathogen genome. Finally, we identify standing variation for adaptation to new climates encountered during the global spread. See below an example of such an analysis for two of the thirteen variables we used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://afeurtey.github.io/images/1000_Zt_GEA.png&#34; alt=&#34;Example of a Manhattan plot from the GEA analysis using bioclimatic variables&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together, our work demonstrates how a comprehensive panel of genomes enables deep insights into the evolutionary history of a major crop pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genomic and epigenomic architecture of a plant pathogen</title>
      <link>https://afeurtey.github.io/project/genomic_architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 11:45:16 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://afeurtey.github.io/project/genomic_architecture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/s12864-020-06871-w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Link to the publication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antagonistic co-evolution can drive rapid adaptation in pathogens and shape genome architecture. Comparative genome analyses of several fungal pathogens revealed highly variable genomes, for many species characterized by specific repeat-rich genome compartments with exceptionally high sequence variability. Dynamic genome structure may enable fast adaptation to host genetics. The wheat pathogen &lt;em&gt;Zymoseptoria tritici&lt;/em&gt; with its highly variable genome, has emerged as a model organism to study genome evolution of plant pathogens. Here, we compared genomes of &lt;em&gt;Z. tritici&lt;/em&gt; isolates and of sister species infecting wild grasses to address the evolution of genome composition and structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using long-read technology, we sequenced and assembled genomes of &lt;em&gt;Z. ardabiliae&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Z. brevis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Z. pseudotritici&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Z. passerinii&lt;/em&gt;, together with two isolates of &lt;em&gt;Z. tritici&lt;/em&gt;. We report a high extent of genome collinearity among &lt;em&gt;Zymoseptoria&lt;/em&gt; species and high conservation of genomic, transcriptomic and epigenomic signatures of compartmentalization (see image below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://afeurtey.github.io/images/Genome_compartment_circos.png&#34; alt=&#34;Circos plots from Z.tritici and Z.pseudotritici, showing compartmentalization at the genomic, transcriptomic and epigenomic levels&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We identify high gene content variability both within and between species. In addition, such variability is mainly limited to the accessory chromosomes and accessory compartments. Despite strong host specificity and non-overlapping host-range between species, predicted effectors are mainly shared among &lt;em&gt;Zymoseptoria&lt;/em&gt; species, yet exhibiting a high level of presence-absence polymorphism within &lt;em&gt;Z. tritici&lt;/em&gt;. Using in planta transcriptomic data from &lt;em&gt;Z. tritici&lt;/em&gt;, we suggest different roles for the shared orthologs and for the accessory genes during infection of their hosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite previous reports of high genomic plasticity in &lt;em&gt;Z. tritici&lt;/em&gt;, we describe here a high level of conservation in genomic, epigenomic and transcriptomic composition and structure across the genus &lt;em&gt;Zymoseptoria&lt;/em&gt;. The compartmentalized genome allows the maintenance of a functional core genome co-occurring with a highly variable accessory genome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crop-to-wild gene flow in apple trees</title>
      <link>https://afeurtey.github.io/project/apple_tree_crop_wild/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 11:45:16 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://afeurtey.github.io/project/apple_tree_crop_wild/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During my PhD in Tatiana Giraud’s group, I studied the role of inter-specific hybridisations in the evolutionary history of apple trees. I investigated the effect of crop-to-wild gene flow on the conservation of two wild apple tree species:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the European wild apple tree, &lt;em&gt;Malus sylvestris&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Asian wild apple tree, &lt;em&gt;Malus sieversii&lt;/em&gt;, which grows in the Tian Shan mountain forests and is the ancestor of the cultivated apple tree, &lt;em&gt;Malus domestica&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crop-to-wild inter-specific gene flow can be observed in the European wild apple tree, correlated with anthropic activities and threatening the genetic integrity of the wild tree populations, since hybrids do not show any detectable reduction in fitness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote or participated in several publications around this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/eva.12250&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Anthropogenic and natural drivers of gene flow in a temperate wild fruit tree: a basis for conservation and breeding programs in apples&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/eva.12441&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crop-to-wild gene flow and its fitness consequences for a wild fruit tree: Towards a comprehensive conservation strategy of the wild apple in Europe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.15677&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Threat to Asian wild apple trees posed by gene flow from domesticated apple trees and their “pestified” pathogens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://afeurtey.github.io/images/Apple_orchard.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An apple tree picture&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strong Phylogeographic costructure between the anther-smut fungus and its white campion host</title>
      <link>https://afeurtey.github.io/project/costructure_sil_micro/costructure_silene_microbotryum/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 11:45:16 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://afeurtey.github.io/project/costructure_sil_micro/costructure_silene_microbotryum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://afeurtey.github.io/images/Silene_Microbotryum_costr.png&#34; alt=&#34;Pretty plots showing the costructure between the plant and its pathogen&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the link to our &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.14125&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;publication&lt;/a&gt; on this topic. We also were very honored to have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.14203&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;commentary&lt;/a&gt; written about this paper by Daniel Croll and Anna-Liisa Laine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While congruence between host and pathogen phylogenies has been extensively investigated, the congruence between host and pathogen genetic structures at the within-species level has received little attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using an unprecedented and comprehensive collection of associated plant-pathogen samples, we investigated the degree of congruence between the genetic structures across Europe of two evolutionary and ecological model organisms, the anther-smut pathogen &lt;em&gt;Microbotryum lychnidis-dioicae&lt;/em&gt; and its host plant &lt;em&gt;Silene latifolia&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We demonstrated a significant and particularly strong level of host-pathogen costructure, with three main genetic clusters displaying highly similar spatial ranges in Western, Eastern Europe, and Italy, respectively. Correcting for the geographical component of genetic variation, significant correlations were still found between the genetic distances among the anther-smut populations paired with its host. Inoculation experiments suggested plant or fungal local adaptation depending on the populations.
These findings indicate that the pathogen has remained isolated in the same fragmented southern refugia as its host plant during the last glaciation, and that little long-distance dispersal has occurred since the recolonization of Europe in neither the plant nor the pathogen, despite their known ability to travel across continents. This, together with the inoculation results, suggests that coevolutionary and competitive processes may be involved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
