<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Coevolution | Alice Feurtey</title>
    <link>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/tag/coevolution/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://academic-demo.netlify.app/tag/coevolution/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Coevolution</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 11:45:16 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Coevolution</title>
      <link>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/tag/coevolution/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crop-to-wild gene flow in apple trees</title>
      <link>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/project/apple_tree_crop_wild/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 11:45:16 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/project/apple_tree_crop_wild/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During my PhD in Tatiana Giraud’s group, I studied the role of inter-specific hybridisations in the evolutionary history of apple trees. I investigated the effect of crop-to-wild gene flow on the conservation of two wild apple tree species:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the European wild apple tree, &lt;em&gt;Malus sylvestris&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Asian wild apple tree, &lt;em&gt;Malus sieversii&lt;/em&gt;, which grows in the Tian Shan mountain forests and is the ancestor of the cultivated apple tree, &lt;em&gt;Malus domestica&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crop-to-wild inter-specific gene flow can be observed in the European wild apple tree, correlated with anthropic activities and threatening the genetic integrity of the wild tree populations, since hybrids do not show any detectable reduction in fitness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote or participated in several publications around this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/eva.12250&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Anthropogenic and natural drivers of gene flow in a temperate wild fruit tree: a basis for conservation and breeding programs in apples&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/eva.12441&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crop-to-wild gene flow and its fitness consequences for a wild fruit tree: Towards a comprehensive conservation strategy of the wild apple in Europe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.15677&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Threat to Asian wild apple trees posed by gene flow from domesticated apple trees and their “pestified” pathogens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://academic-demo.netlify.app/images/Apple_orchard.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An apple tree picture&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strong Phylogeographic costructure between the anther-smut fungus and its white campion host</title>
      <link>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/project/costructure_sil_micro/costructure_silene_microbotryum/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 11:45:16 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://academic-demo.netlify.app/project/costructure_sil_micro/costructure_silene_microbotryum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://academic-demo.netlify.app/images/Silene_Microbotryum_costr.png&#34; alt=&#34;Pretty plots showing the costructure between the plant and its pathogen&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the link to our &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.14125&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;publication&lt;/a&gt; on this topic. We also were very honored to have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.14203&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;commentary&lt;/a&gt; written about this paper by Daniel Croll and Anna-Liisa Laine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While congruence between host and pathogen phylogenies has been extensively investigated, the congruence between host and pathogen genetic structures at the within-species level has received little attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using an unprecedented and comprehensive collection of associated plant-pathogen samples, we investigated the degree of congruence between the genetic structures across Europe of two evolutionary and ecological model organisms, the anther-smut pathogen &lt;em&gt;Microbotryum lychnidis-dioicae&lt;/em&gt; and its host plant &lt;em&gt;Silene latifolia&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We demonstrated a significant and particularly strong level of host-pathogen costructure, with three main genetic clusters displaying highly similar spatial ranges in Western, Eastern Europe, and Italy, respectively. Correcting for the geographical component of genetic variation, significant correlations were still found between the genetic distances among the anther-smut populations paired with its host. Inoculation experiments suggested plant or fungal local adaptation depending on the populations.
These findings indicate that the pathogen has remained isolated in the same fragmented southern refugia as its host plant during the last glaciation, and that little long-distance dispersal has occurred since the recolonization of Europe in neither the plant nor the pathogen, despite their known ability to travel across continents. This, together with the inoculation results, suggests that coevolutionary and competitive processes may be involved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
