<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alice Feurtey on Alice Feurtey.</title>
    <link>https://afeurtey.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Alice Feurtey on Alice Feurtey.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2022 11:45:16 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://afeurtey.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Global spread and adaptation of a major crop pathogen</title>
      <link>https://afeurtey.github.io/current-project/thousands_zt_genomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2022 11:45:16 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://afeurtey.github.io/current-project/thousands_zt_genomes/</guid>
      <description>This is an ongoing project and is described here only for information. The figures are from talks I have made and they are likely to change as this project evolves and until it gets published officially.
 Human activity has a tremendous impact on the evolutionary trajectories of many species worldwide. Global trade of agricultural goods contributes to the dispersal of domesticated species but also of their pathogens, reshaping species distributions to include new environments and climates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genomic and epigenomic architecture of a plant pathogen</title>
      <link>https://afeurtey.github.io/publication/genomic_architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 11:45:16 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://afeurtey.github.io/publication/genomic_architecture/</guid>
      <description>Using several fully assembled &lt;em&gt;Zymoseptoria&lt;/em&gt; genomes, we describe here a high level of conservation in genomic, epigenomic and transcriptomic composition and structure across the genus &lt;em&gt;Zymoseptoria&lt;/em&gt;, despite previous reports of high genomic plasticity in &lt;em&gt;Z. tritici&lt;/em&gt;. The compartmentalized genome allows the maintenance of a functional core genome co-occurring with a highly variable accessory genome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crop-to-wild gene flow in apple trees</title>
      <link>https://afeurtey.github.io/publication/apple_trees_crop_wild/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 11:45:16 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://afeurtey.github.io/publication/apple_trees_crop_wild/</guid>
      <description>During my Master&amp;rsquo;s and PhD projects, in Tatiana Giraud’s group, I studied the role of inter-specific hybridisations in the evolutionary history of apple trees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strong Phylogeographic costructure between the anther-smut fungus and its white campion host</title>
      <link>https://afeurtey.github.io/publication/costructure_silene_microbotryum/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 11:45:16 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://afeurtey.github.io/publication/costructure_silene_microbotryum/</guid>
      <description>We demonstrated a significant and particularly strong level of host-pathogen costructure between the anther-smut pathogen Microbotryum lychnidis-dioicae and its host plant Silene latifolia. his, together with the inoculation results, suggests that coevolutionary and competitive processes are involved in the evolution of these two species.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://afeurtey.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://afeurtey.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>This is my website, welcome! Here, you will find my past research projects as well as some on-going research or data science project.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
